ACCION International Records MS196
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
ACCION International Records
1960 -- 2005
1950 -- 2012
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
ACCION International
MS196
129.2 Linear Feet
238 Audiovisual Object(s)
558 Digital Object(s)
2 Web sites
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 12 series: Origins and founding documents; Board of Directors records; CEO records; Financial records; Communications and External Affairs records; Resource Development records; Human Resources records; Center for Financial Inclusion records; Global Programs records; Administrative records; Strategic planning records; and Conference records.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the operations of ACCION International, a global nonprofit institution specializing in microfinance.
Records include executive office and departmental files; financial records; the records of centers, programs, and initiatives; and conference materials. In addition to correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, reports, and publications, there are audiovisual materials and photographs. The bulk of the collection dates from 1960 to 2005 and primarily relates to ACCION's programs and microfinance institutions (MFIs) in Latin America, the Caribbean, and the United States; there is also some material pertaining to ACCION's operations in Africa and Asia.
The files and papers of several key ACCION employees are integrated into the collection. This includes presidents and CEOs Michael Chu (1993-1999) and Maria Otero (2000-2009); Carlos Castello, executive vice president and head of Global Programs (2006-2016); Susana Barton, vice president and program manager (2004-2012); and Cathy Quense, chief financial officer (1996-2008).
Biographical / Historical
ACCION International was founded in 1961 by Joseph H. Blatchford, a recent graduate from the University of California, Berkeley Law School. Moved to action by the political upheaval and poverty he saw traveling in Latin America, Blatchford viewed community grassroots development as a way to help improve lives. In 1961, he enlisted the help of two other UC Berkeley students, Jerry Brady and Gary Glenn, to recruit the first class of thirty American volunteers to work on their first projects in Venezuela.
ACCION's initial projects involved improving infrastructure in the community through both fundraising and manual labor such as building schools and digging ditches. They also worked to provide technical support and assistance, enabling local residents to embark on their own projects. Blatchford expanded ACCION with chapters in Brazil, Peru, and New York in the late 1960s. In the first decade of ACCION's existence, the news media frequently made comparisons between the organization and the Peace Corps. Blatchford was appointed Director of the Peace Corps in 1969.
In the 1970s, ACCION sought to address lack of economic opportunity in urban Latin America by establishing a microlending program. In 1973 the ACCION organization UNO (Recife, Brazil), issued its first loans to small, informal enterprises. ACCION's success in microlending led to their subsequent focus on microfinance. From 1980 to 1990, ACCION established microfinance programs in fourteen Latin American and Caribbean countries. In 1984, ACCION created the Latin American Bridge Fund, a guaranteed fund through which ACCION affiliates could secure lines of credit.
The Gran Salto "Great Leap" expansion campaign of the 1990s developed ACCION's programs in the United States as well as extending their reach in Latin America. In 1991, ACCION founded the ACCION U.S. Network to create microfinance programs in the United States. The pilot program was launched in Brooklyn, New York and the program grew steadily across the United States.
In 1992, ACCION joined with nonprofit microlender PRODEM and other local banks and investors to found BancoSol, the world's first commercial bank focused solely on microfinance, in Bolivia. ACCION established the Gateway Fund to make investments in microfinance institutions worldwide in 1996 and continued to expand its international operations outside the Americas in the 2000s by establishing partnerships with aspiring small business owners in sub-Saharan Africa and India. A partnership with Ecobank led to the founding of EB-Accion Savings and Loans in Ghana in 2007.
ACCION established the Center for Financial Inclusion (CFI), a think tank dedicated to taking action to ensure broad access to financial services, in 2008. CFI has collaborated with microfinance experts, financial advisers, banking institutions, investors, and a number of other stakeholders to achieve its goals of financial inclusion.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Specific restrictions are noted in the detailed contents list in each series.
Blatchford, Joseph H., 1934-; Borrowing and lending; Economics.; Grants and funding; Microfinance.; Microfinance--Africa.; Microfinance--Developing countries.; Microfinance--India.; Microfinance--Latin America.; Microfinance--Research.; Microfinance--United States.; MicroFinance Network; Otero, María; United States. Agency for International Development.; Finance
- Origins and founding records, 1960 -- 2016; MS196.001; 8.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records detailing the origins and creation of ACCION International. These records include correspondence, project reports, clippings from the 1960s and 1970s, financials, bylaws and corporate records, press releases, pamphlets, and information bulletins from ACCION Venezuela and ACCION Colombia from the 1960s, as well as The Politics of the Barrios of Venezuela byTalton F. Ray, and letterhead. The bulk of the materials are from 1960-1973, dating from the founding of ACCION to the creation of UNO. UNO was a small pilot program started in 1972 in Recife, Brazil that began ACCION's work in microfinance.
  Correspondence includes letters between ACCION founder Joseph H. Blatchford and various foundations, government offices, universities and colleges, corporations, and individuals applying and participating in the program. Project reports from Maricabo, Venezuela, document some of the earliest projects of ACCION. This series also contains information put together by ACCION's Department of Communication and External Affairs that outlines the growth of the company and provides contextual information about its origins and founding. This material was used in part for publicity and for staff training.
  Arrangement
  This material is minimally processed and arranged in received order. The material was collected and arranged by Robin Radcliffe, the vice president of communications, prior to her retirement in 2011. Two accessions (2013.123 and 2015.020) were consolidated, arranged at the container level, and added to this series in 2016 by Rose Oliveira.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - ACCION History and Summary of Projects, 1961 -- 2011; MS196.001.001.00001; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION International Staff Meeting - May, 1966, MS196.001.001.00002 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Staff lists: directors, administrators, volunteers, 1961 -- 1969; MS196.001.001.00003 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Sample ACCION Letterhead and Application, 1961 -- 1973; MS196.001.001.00004 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - External Affairs: Annual Reports, 1964 -- 1969; MS196.001.001.00005 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - External Affairs: Brocures/Pamphlets, 1974; MS196.001.001.00006 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - External Affairs: Publications, 1961 -- 1974; MS196.001.001.00007 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - External Affairs: Newsletters, 1971; MS196.001.001.00008 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Financial, Tax, Investment, 1964 -- 1974; MS196.001.001.00009 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Legal and Corporate Records: By-Laws, 1973; MS196.001.001.00010 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - External Affairs: Media Coverage and Correspondence, 1964 -- 1974; MS196.001.001.00011 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Board of Directors Pack 11-99, 1999; MS196.001.001.00012 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Readers' Digest - September 1961 - ACCION speaks louder than words, 1962; MS196.001.001.00013 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Press Clips 60s and 70s, 1961 -- 1989; MS196.001.001.00014 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Venezuela, 1961 -- 1967; MS196.001.001.00015 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Colombia - Information booklets, 1970; MS196.001.001.00016 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Colombia - Boletin Informativo 1-6, 1971; MS196.001.001.00017 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Colombia - Memorando Informativo, 1972; MS196.001.001.00018 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Colombia - Corporacion de Accion Social Emprasarial [Information Packet Contents], 1971 -- 1972; MS196.001.001.00019 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - ACCION en Colombia - Corporacion de Accion Social Emprasarial [Information Packet Folder], 1971 -- 1972; MS196.001.001.00020 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Accion International History, 1990 -- 2010; MS196.001.001.00021 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Accion History, 1987 -- 1990; MS196.001.001.00022 (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - First decade origins and founding, 1960 -- 1968; MS196.001.043 (Box 43)
  - Early history of ACCION and Accion en Venezuela records, circa 1965 -- 2016; MS196.002836 (Box 98, Folder 4)
- Board of Directors records, 1963 -- 2012; MS196.002; 6.1 Linear Feet; 65 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains board packets, meeting minutes, correspondence, memoranda, bylaws, notes, manuals, reports, and electronic files of the Board of Directors. The bulk of this material ranges from 1998 to 2008 and documents the decisions and actions of the Board of Directors. Also included are materials from several committees and councils including the Gateway Investment Committee, Nominating Committees, Advisory Council, and the Ad Hoc Strategy and Risk Committee. Board packets include lists of attendees, correspondence, agendas, minutes, committee and program reports, topics of discussion, and addenda. Some board packets are annotated by Cathy Quense or Roy Jacobowitz .These materials document changes to the bylaws, the development of programs and initiatives, and problems and solutions discussed by the board.
  This material is minimally processed and arranged in received order. Materials from accession 2015.020 were added to the beginning of box 044.
  20 years from date of creation. Open for research.
  - Accion in Venezuela, 1965-02-18; MS196.002.00001
  - Accion launch, 1965-10-04; MS196.002.00002
  - Article - Brazil, 1967-04-05; MS196.002.00003
  - Report on activities of Accion International, 1966-04-01; MS196.002.00004
  - Brazil: Interim progress report, 1966-05-31; MS196.002.00005
  - Report on activities, 1966-06-22; MS196.002.00006
  - Report on Accion International activities, 1966-10-06; MS196.002.00007
  - Annual Report Pursuant to Section 45 of the Membership Corporations Law of the State of New York, 1965; MS196.002.00008
  - Report of the Board of Directors to the members of the corporation, 1966; MS196.002.00009
  - Report of the Board of Directors to the members of the corporation, 1967; MS196.002.00010
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1966-01-25; MS196.002.00011
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1967-05-01; MS196.002.00012
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1976-05-11; MS196.002.00013
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1977-06-01; MS196.002.00014
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1992-06-02; MS196.002.00015
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1991-05-05; MS196.002.00016
  - Strategic plan, 1994-06-10; MS196.002.00017
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1993-06-14; MS196.002.00018
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1966-06-27; MS196.002.00019
  - Postponed annual meeting, board of directors, 1969-09-22; MS196.002.00020
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1975-10-22; MS196.002.00021
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1965-11-30; MS196.002.00022
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1977-12-01; MS196.002.00023
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1980-12-04; MS196.002.00024
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1992-12-04; MS196.002.00025
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1976-12-09; MS196.002.00026
  - Board of directors meeting, 1968-12-10; MS196.002.00027
  - Board of directors meeting, 1969-12-10; MS196.002.00028
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1967-12-11; MS196.002.00029
  - Meeting of the Board of Directors - agenda, 1966-12-12; MS196.002.00030
  - Corporate funders, 1965-07-07; MS196.002.00031
  - Corporation funding contact - pending, 1966-09-21; MS196.002.00032
  - Executive committee meeting minutes, 1970 -- 1980; MS196.002.00033
  - Executive committee meeting minutes, 1981 -- 1989; MS196.002.00034
  - Accion International contributors, 1966-12-09; MS196.002.00035
  - Funding contacts, 1966-10-03; MS196.002.00036
  - Funding contacts, 1966-12; MS196.002.00037
  - Funding report, 1966; MS196.002.00038
  - Call and waiver of notice of meeting of incorporators of Accion International, 1965-06-21; MS196.002.00039
  - Funds outstanding, 1966-07-01; MS196.002.00040
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1966-01-25; MS196.002.00041
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1969-02-11; MS196.002.00042
  - Minutes, 1965-02-25; MS196.002.00043
  - Minutes of U.S. Committee, 1965-04-30; MS196.002.00044
  - Minutes of postponed annual meeting of directors, 1967-05-01; MS196.002.00045
  - Minutes of postponed annual meeting of directors, 1970-05-14; MS196.002.00046
  - Minutes of the first meeting of the board of directors, 1965-06-23; MS196.002.00047
  - Minutes of postponed annual meeting of directors, 1968-06-25; MS196.002.00048
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1966-06-27; MS196.002.00049
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1965-08-16; MS196.002.00050
  - Minutes of postponed annual meeting of directors, 1969-09-22; MS196.002.00051
  - Minutes of meeting of trustees and members, 1963-10-03; MS196.002.00052
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1967-11-09; MS196.002.00053
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1965-11-30; MS196.002.00054
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1968-12-10; MS196.002.00055
  - Minutes of a special meeting of the board of directors, 1967-12-11; MS196.002.00056
  - Minutes of special meeting of board of directors, 1966-07-01; MS196.002.00057
  - Minutes of meeting of executive committee of the board of directors, 1969-12-17; MS196.002.00058
  - Minutes of the meeting of the board of directors, 1971 -- 1993; MS196.002.00059
  - Correspondence, 1968; MS196.002.00060
  - Neumann's remarks to AI board of directors, 1967-12-12; MS196.002.00061
  - Progress Report, 1965-06-16; MS196.002.00062
  - Survey trip to Brazil, 1966-03-25; MS196.002.00063
  - Texas memo, 1966-06-27; MS196.002.00064
  - Board of directors files, 1990 -- 2012; MS196.002.00065
    20 years from date of creation.
    Board of directors files
  - Board of Director packets, 1999 -- 2011; MS196.002.044; Quense, Cathy (Box 44)
  - Board of Director packets, 1998 -- 2011; MS196.002.045; Quense, Cathy (Box 45)
  - Board meeting and notes, 1995 -- 2010; MS196.002.046; Quense, Cathy (Box 46)
  - Board, council, and committee meetings, 1989 -- 2010; MS196.002.047; Quense, Cathy (Box 47)
  - Board of Directors meeting packets, 1975 -- 2006; MS196.002837 (Box 97)
  - Board of Directors meeting packets, 2007 -- 2010; MS196.002838 (Box 98, Folder 6-8)
- CEO records, 1993 -- 2009; MS196.003; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series includes correspondence, reports, notes, press releases, electronic files, and a briefing book that document the work of ACCION International chief executive officers. The bulk of the materials range from 1993 to 1995 and documents ACCION's programs including high level summaries of ACCION's work with Corposol, a Colombian microfinance institution. Also included are Maria Otero's statements before the United States House of Representatives Committee on International Relations and articles written by Michael Chu on microfinance. Electronic files contain speeches from the files of Bruce MacDonald in Communications, and correspondence from the files of Ellen Bauer in the Executive Office.
  These materials come from the files of Cathy Quense, chief financial officer (CFO) (1996-2008) and chief deputy/chief administrative officer (2008-2012), and Michael Chu, president and CEO (1993-1999).
  This material is minimally processed and is arranged in its received order. Two boxes from different accessions (2013.123.and 2015.020) were consolidated.
  - Correspondence and reports, 1993 -- 2009; MS196.003.048; Chu, Michael; Quense, Cathy (Box 48)
- Financial records, 1985 -- 2011; MS196.005; 1.2 Linear Feet; 18 Digital Object(s); 25.9 Megabytes
  This series contains budgets, financial statements, memoranda, minutes, notes, presentations, and other records of ACCION International's Audit, Finance and Investment Committee. The financial statements and meeting minutes provide information about ACCION's investments, insurance policies, revenue streams, and expenses. Also included are supplementary meeting materials, such as newspaper columns and articles, circulated to members of the committee in advance of each meeting.
  Two folders of Cathy Quense's files include her own meeting notes, memoranda, and written presentations.
  This series is restricted 20 years from date of creation.
  This series is arranged in received order, which is roughly chronological.
  75 years from the date of creation.
  - Financial records: Cathy Quense files, 1985 -- 2005; MS196.005.089; Quense, Cathy (Box 89)
  - Internal Revenue Service 990 forms and audits, 1995 -- 2011; MS196.002833; 25.9 Megabytes; 18 Digital Object(s)
    75 years from date of creation.
- Communications and External Affairs records, 1950 -- 2012; 1985 -- 2005; MS196.006; 62.7 Linear Feet; 238 Audiovisual Object(s); 365 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains annual reports, press releases, speeches, conference records, reprints, clippings, pamphlets, bulletins, and other materials created by ACCION International's office of Communications and External Affairs. Also included are marketing presentations, photographs, promotional videos and commercials, audio and video segments from news broadcasts and interviews, media pitches, event records, and administrative records including correspondence, memos, planning documents, and media contact sheets. The bulk of the materials date from 1985 to 2005. Communications and External Affairs was responsible for ACCION's communications and marketing programs, including branding, outreach, media affairs, digital marketing, internal communications, events, publications, public relations, and development.
  Speeches by ACCION executive officers, such as Michael Chu and Maria Otero, in sub-series 002 are of particular note and provide important contextual information about the views and goals of the organization's leadership. Additionally, there is abundant material in the series that documents ACCION's participation in the Microcredit Summit Campaign, established in 1997. Hillary Clinton was the keynote speaker at the first Microcredit Summit, held in Washington, D.C. in February 1997. Other materials in sub-series 003 and 004 document ACCION's working relationship with Hillary Clinton on projects, such as the Clinton Global Initiative, related to poverty reduction in Asia and Latin America.
  Materials are in English and Spanish.
  This series is arranged in six sub-series: Annual reports; Communication and development files; Vice President of Communications records; Reprints and publicity; Publications; and Photographs and audiovisual materials.
  Physical condition. 75 years from the date of creation. 20 years from date of creation. Open for research.
  - Annual reports, 1964 -- 2011; MS196.006.001; 1.2 Linear Feet
    This sub-series contains ACCION International's Annual reports from 1964-2010, annual reports for ACCION USA from 1999-2005, and annual reports from regional branches from 1996-2008. Many of the reports are in Spanish.
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically by organization (ACCION International, ACCION USA, ACCION Regional Branches).
    - Annual Reports, 1964 -- 1967; MS196.006.001.001.00023; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
      ACCION International (Organization)
    - Annual Reports, 1975 -- 1976; MS196.006.001.001.00024; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International, 1981 -- 1989; MS196.006.001.001.00025; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International - Folder 1 of 2, 1990 -- 1994; MS196.006.001.001.00026; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International - Folder 2 of 2, 1995 -- 1999; MS196.006.001.001.00027; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International - Folder 1 of 3, 2000 -- 2006; MS196.006.001.001.00028; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International - Folder 2 of 3, 2006 -- 2008; MS196.006.001.001.00029; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion International - Folder 3 of 3, 2009 -- 2010; MS196.006.001.001.00030; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Accion USA, 1999 -- 2005; MS196.006.001.001.00031; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Regional Branches Folder 1 of 2, 1996 -- 1998; MS196.006.001.001.00032; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports - Regional Branches Folder 2 of 2, 1995 -- 2008; MS196.006.001.001.00033; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Strategic Plans and Progress Reports, 1984 -- 1997; MS196.006.001.001.00034; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Impact Evaluations, 1988; MS196.006.001.001.00035; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
    - Annual Reports, 2011; MS196.006.001.001.00036; ACCION International (Organization) (Box MS196 Shared 1)
  - Communication and development files, 1981 -- 2002; MS196.006.002; 14.4 Linear Feet
    This sub-series contains records relating to ACCION International's outward communication and development including awards, press releases, listings, conference and meeting files, speeches and staff presentations. The files in this series are a record of ACCION's efforts to advertise and promote the organization. Listings are records of their advertisements and other mention of ACCION in print media. Press releases are announcements sent to media outlets for release and include job announcements for upper management, announcements for events, conferences and major projects. Conference and meeting files contain schedules, notes, summaries, memos, correspondence, and planning material for conferences and other meetings hosted and attended by ACCION staff. Conferences and meetings include but are not limited to: Microenterprise Development Conference, Congress of the Americas: World Economic Development, Congrencia de Directores, DAI Workshop on Microenterprise Finance and Development, Harvard Latin American Business Conference, CGAP Consultative Forum, Microfinance Network Conference, and the Microcredit Summit.
    This sub-series is arranged in original order, which is roughly chronological.
    - Listings Folder 1 of 2, 1996 -- 1999; MS196.006.002.002.00001; ACCION International (Organization) (Box 2)